<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dorcas: a true patterne of a goodly life, and good end With a pithy exhortation to the practice of faith and good works. In a sermon preached at Totnes in Deuon, Ianuary 14 16[...] at the funerall of Mrs. Mary Bab, widow. By Thomas Saltern, sometimes lecturer there; and preacher of the word at Bradford. And now published, at the request of sundry godly persons.</title>
            <author>Saltern, Thomas, b. 1579 or 80.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847397</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dorcas: a true patterne of a goodly life, and good end With a pithy exhortation to the practice of faith and good works. In a sermon preached at Totnes in Deuon, Ianuary 14 16[...] at the funerall of Mrs. Mary Bab, widow. By Thomas Saltern, sometimes lecturer there; and preacher of the word at Bradford. And now published, at the request of sundry godly persons.</title>
                  <author>Saltern, Thomas, b. 1579 or 80.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. F[lesher] for Roger Iackson, and are to bee sold at his shop neere the Conduit in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The Bodleian Library copy and the Yale University copy have imprint date altered in ink to read 1631; the Bodleian copy has date of sermon's delivery in title altered to 1630--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; date in title and imprint altered affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12430:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12430:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DORCAS:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A TRVE PATTERNE of a goodly life, and good end.</p>
            <p>WITH. A PITHY EXHORTATION to the practice of faith and good works.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at <hi>Totnes</hi> in <hi>Deuon,</hi> Ianuary 14. 1630 <hi>At the Funerall of</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Mary Bab, <hi>Widow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS SALTERN, ſometimes Lecturer there; And Preacher of the Word at <hi>Bradford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now publiſhed, at the requeſt of ſundry godly perſons.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 31.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Fauour is deceitfull, and beauty is vaine, but a woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop neere the Conduit in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12430:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12430:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DORCAS,</hi> A PATTERNE OF a godly life, and good end.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 9. verſ. 36, 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now there was at <hi>Ioppa</hi> a certaine Diſciple, named <hi>Tabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> which by interpretation is called <hi>Dorcas:</hi> This woman was full of good workes, and almeſ-deeds which ſhee did.</p>
                  <p>And it came to paſſe in thoſe dayes that ſhe was ſicke, and dyed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole Chapter may well be diuided into two parts: the one concerning Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the other touching Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> the one the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the other of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> The ones wonderfull conuerſion, the others mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous operation: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the one from a Wolfe into a Lambe, from a Beare into a Sheep, from plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> into following the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah:</hi> from <hi>Saul</hi> into <hi>Paul:</hi> from a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, into a Preacher of Chriſtianity. The others miraculous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration in healing a ſicke man at <hi>Lydda,</hi> in raiſing a dead Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12430:3"/> at <hi>Ioppa:</hi> both workes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, but the latter more, by how much more harder it is to giue life to one that is dead, then to reſtore health <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n one that is ſicke. In this later ſtory, beſides many other circumſtances that may bee noted, I obſerue vnto you theſe three: Firſt, the perſon raiſed to life, <hi>Tabitha,</hi> which by interpretation is called <hi>Dorcas.</hi> Secondly, the inſtrument which God vſed in the raiſing of her, <hi>viz.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> Thirdly, the effect of the miracle, which <hi>v.</hi> 42, is intimated to bee two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, fame brought to the eares, and faith bred in the hearts of many people; <hi>for it was knowne throughout all</hi> Ioppa, <hi>and many beleeued in the Lord.</hi> I will ſpeake onely of the perſon raiſed, for my text ſtretcheth it ſelfe no further, concerning whom the ſtory records three things, her life, her death, her being raiſed againe. Of the third point nothing at all at this time, for it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not within the bounds and limits of my text: only of the two former, her life, and death; whereof you haue a Sermon in print ſo intituled, <hi>The Life and Death of</hi> DORCAS; to which I will refer you for many good notes; which, becauſe there ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, by me ſhall be omitted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In ſpeaking of her life I will intreat of two things, firſt, of her name, <hi>Tabitha,</hi> by interpretation <hi>Dorcas:</hi> and ſecondly, of her profeſſion; her profeſſion in the forme of it, <hi>ſhee was a Diſciple,</hi> and her profeſſion in the fruit of it, <hi>ſhe was full of good workes and almes which ſhe did.</hi> In intreating of her death, I will ſpeake of two things, the fore-runner of her death, which was her ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the euent of her ſickneſſe, which was her death.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing then to be ſpoken of is her name, <hi>Tabitha,</hi> and that is <hi>Dorcas,</hi> which names doe ſignifie a Roe or a Bucke, and are both of them deriued from ſuch rootes in their ſeuerall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, as doe betoken to ſee. I will ſay nothing of that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation that might here bee made, how that God knoweth his children by name, as he ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 33.17. <hi>Thou haſt found grace in my ſight, and I know thee by name:</hi> to ſhew that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and peculiar knowledge of approbation, whereby God knoweth the elect aboue others; nor any thing of the diſcreet choice that ſhould be vſed in the naming of children; in which point, as I commend not the nicety of ſome, who like no other names, but ſuch as haue their good ſignification in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12430:3"/> ſo I much rather condemne their abſurd folly, who out of wit as they thinke, I am ſure without any dramme of diſcretion, giue ridiculous and vnſeemly names to the children they come to be ſureties for. The note I doe gather out of her name, and I will but touch vpon it, is in a word this, as her name was, ſo was ſhe: <hi>Tabitha,</hi> or <hi>Dorcas</hi> was her name, and ſhe was, and wee ought to bee cleare-ſighted, and with our eyes open, to the things that concerne our ſoules health. In things of the world we are Eagles, but beetles and moles in diuine matters: curious inquiſitors into the liues of other, careleſſe neglecters of our owne eſtates, and of what belongs to our Chriſtian duties; whereas if we would ſearch the Scriptures as wee are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, we ſhould in them be taught what the obiects are, which God would haue vs chiefly to fixe the eyes of our cares and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauors on. <hi>See that you keepe my Sabbaths, Exod.</hi> 31. <hi>See</hi> (ſaid old <hi>Tobit</hi> to his Sonne) <hi>that thou neuer doe that to any man, which thou wouldeſt not that another ſhould doe to thee. Why ſeeſt thou the more in thy brothers eye, and doeſt not ſee the beame in thine owne eye, Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>See that no man deceiue you; See and take heed how you heare; See that you walke circumſpectly, not as fooles, but as wiſe,</hi> Epheſ. 5.15. <hi>See that none recompence euill for euill vnto any man, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.15. And in many other places of holy Scripture we are taught, that if we wil be true <hi>Dorcaſſes</hi> indeed, we muſt caſt our eyes, the eyes of our affections, <hi>not on things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but on the things that are aboue,</hi> Colloſ. 3.2. Therefore did <hi>Dauid</hi> pray vnto God, ſaying, <hi>Turne away mine eyes that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold not vanity. But I haue ſeene</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) and conſidered all the workes that are done vnder the Sun, and behold, all is vanity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.14.</p>
            <p>The next thing to bee ſpoken of in the life of this <hi>Dorcas,</hi> is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> her profeſſion, which was not in ſhew onely, and for formalities ſake; but in deed, and in truth: <hi>She was a Diſciple, and full of good workes &amp; almes which ſhe did.</hi> A diſciple in profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in practice too, a diſciple in confeſſion and conuerſation too; the one by her faith, and the other by her workes, the one is as the roote, the other as the fruit of Chriſtian profeſſion. They met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in her, and muſt in all that will be true diſciples: <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. and <hi>without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12430:4"/> impoſſible to ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Faith without workes is dead, and workes without faith, are ſinnes, not in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and becauſe they are done; but in a maine circumſtance, becauſe done without faith.</p>
            <p>Morall honeſty, without profeſſion of the true faith, is blind, and wanteth an eye to direct it; and profeſſion, without practice, on the other ſide, is lame, and wants a foot to cary it in the way to heauen. Therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, I beſeech you that you walke worthy of the vocation wherewith you are called,</hi> Epheſ. 4.1. And, <hi>let your conuerſation be as becommeth the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Phi. 1.27. that the Goſpell of Chriſt, the profeſſion of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the name of diſciples, the truth of God bee not ill ſpoken of, as the Apoſtle telleth the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The name of God is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed among the Gentiles through you,</hi> Rom. 2.24. and willeth <hi>Titus</hi> to teach all degrees ſo to behaue themſelues, <hi>that the word of God be not blaſphemed,</hi> Tit. 2.5. for if we play the fooliſh pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters part, and <hi>humane capiti ceruicem adiungere equinam,</hi> put a mans head on an horſes necke, looke like diſciples, and liue like Deuills, confeſſe God in our mouthes, and deny him in our workes, ſhall it not be ſaid of vs in ſcorne and deriſion, as it was of the <hi>Iewes</hi> by the Heathen, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.20. <hi>Theſe are the people of the Lord,</hi> theſe are the Proteſtants of our times, theſe are the Profeſſors of our dayes, theſe are they that call themſelues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and are not; <hi>But as many as walke according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and vpon the Iſrael of God,</hi> Gal. 6.16.</p>
            <p>O beloued, when the doctrines and deeds, the words and workes, the profeſſion and practice of Chriſtians, of Diſciples, of Profeſſors, ſhall not agree together, but be at oddes and at iarre with one another, conſider and thinke on it in the feare of God, what aduantage you giue to any the enemies of God and his Truth, of Chriſt and his Religion, of goodneſſe and good men, to ſpeake euill of your God, to lay a blemiſh on your Religion, to condemne your profeſſion, becauſe they will not eaſily bee made to thinke that there can be any good root or foundation there, where they ſee no better fruit, ſo bad a building. This holineſſe of life, (I mean not that alone which the Philoſophers ſpeake of, and we call it morall honeſty, which yet commends vs vnto the world, is good in it ſelfe, is neceſſary to ſaluation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12430:4"/> but is not ſufficient) when it is the fruit and effect of a liuely faith in Chriſt Ieſus, and a right affection to Godward, is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and teſtimony of our vnion with Chriſt, of our ſtate in grace, of our being as we would bee taken for, true diſciples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: a teſtimony I ſay, and a token, not to our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces only, but to other mens hearts alſo; wheras to profeſſe well, and liue ill, or to make a ſhift to liue morally ciuill, and not care of what profeſſion we be, is to beare falſe witneſſe againſt God, whoſe ſeruants we boaſt our ſelues, and would be taken for, and yet haue not on his liuery: Gods liuery is a good life, and the badge or cognizance thereof, is a right profeſſion; this ioyntly is it which ſhould, this is it which doth, this is it which will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, when words ſhall proue but winde, and ſhewes ſhall bee but ſhadowes, whoſe ſeruants we are in deed. Wee all deſire, and are glad to bee accounted good Chriſtians, honeſt men, true profeſſors, the children of God, faithfull brethren, and the like; but let vs ſtriue to be what we deſire to be accounted; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly names will neuer iuſtifie godleſſe men, nay, <hi>pium nomen eſt reatus impij,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saluianus,</hi> wee are but openly mockt and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided, ſecretly accuſed and conuicted, when we are honoured with names and titles, whereto our liues and manners are not ſutable. Therefore try your ſelues, beloued, what meaſure of righteouſneſſe is in you, let not the names of honeſt men, and good Chriſtians, and ſuch other, puffe any of you vp; try and examine your owne hearts, with what loue you heare the word, with what care you are fitted to doe thereafter, what conſcience you make of ſinne, what ioy you conceiue in the workes of righteouſneſſe, what griefe you feele when your frailty doth make you to fall; thus try, and ſo like or diſlike of your ſelues. Certainely a Chriſtian, though he cannot be <hi>ſine peccato &amp; cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> without ſinne; yet he ſhould labour to be <hi>ſine crimine &amp; quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rela,</hi> without being ſcandalous and offenſiue. No man ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to ſay abſolutely as Chriſt did, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.46. <hi>Which of you can conuince me of ſin? for in many things we offend all,</hi> Iam. 3.2. And, <hi>if we ſay that wee haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and the the truth is not in vs,</hi> 1 Iohn 1.8. And therefore wee pray with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 143.2. <hi>Enter not into iudgment with thy ſeruants:</hi> Yet in reſpect of men, and of the world, we ought all of vs to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12430:5"/> and endeauor, to ſtriue with might and maine, to bee able to ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.15. <hi>I haue not taken ſo much as an Aſſe from them, neither haue I hurt any of them;</hi> as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> did to the people, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Beheld, here I am, beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of me before the Lord, and before his Anointed, Whoſe Oxe haue I taken? or whoſe Aſſe haue I taken? or whom haue I done wrong to? or whom haue I hurt? &amp;c.</hi> As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.4. <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe.</hi> So to liue in ſincerity of heart, that we may be able to ſay with <hi>Iob, We haue our witneſſe in heauen, and a witneſſe in our owne conſciences;</hi> and outwardly to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch integrity and righteouſneſſe, as that we dare challenge either common fame to accuſe vs, or our very enemies to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs if they can. And in thus doing, wee ſhall bring glory to God, comfort to our owne conſciences, and benefit vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. God ſhall be glorified; and therefore ſaith S. <hi>Peter, Haue your conuerſation honeſt among the Gentiles, that they which ſpeake euill of you as of euill doers, may by your good workes which they ſhall ſee, glorifie God in the day of the viſitation.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.12. Others <hi>ſhall be aſhamed hauing nothing concerning you to ſpeake euill of,</hi> Tit. 2.8. and by this good ſhame won vnto the word through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of the reſt; and aboue all, our owne conſciences ſhall receiue that peace and quiet which the world cannot giue, nor the vnderſtanding of man comprehend. And ſo I come to ſpeak more particularly of the fruit of this womans profeſſion, out of thoſe words, <hi>ſhe was full of good workes, and almes which ſhe did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In which words the fruit of her profeſſion is commended, from the matter of it, from the meaſure of it, from the quality, from the quantity of it; the matter or quality twofold, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>good workes,</hi> in ſpeciall <hi>almeſdeedes;</hi> the meaſure and quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the word <hi>full, full of good workes, and full of almes.</hi> Firſt, <hi>full of good workes.</hi> Now when I ſpeake of good workes, I will not bound and impale them within the too narrow compaſſe of the workes of mercy onely, and charity towards men; nor doe I thinke my text inforceth me ſo to doe: neither will I ſpeake in the language of Gentiliſme, that knoweth no other good works then thoſe which we call morall vertues; no, the ſeuerall fruits of faith, the many branches growing out of the tree of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, the ſeuerall Commandements of the two
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12430:5"/> Tables, are not more wide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of good works is. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is commanded in any of thoſe precepts (faith it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone excepted, which is included in the firſt Commandement, is comprehended vnder the name and title of good workes: euen as the proper branches of our faith doe ſpread themſelues as far as the Articles of our Creed doe; the ſum of that which a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to beleeue to his ſoules health.</p>
            <p>Let no man therefore thinke it enough for him to bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and zealous in performing the Commandements of the firſt Table, while thoſe of the ſecond Table are neglected by him, if not by his open or actuall tranſgreſſion of the letter, yet by too ordinary violating the ſenſe of them, in his truely diſobeying vnder an vntrue pretence of greater obedience, by his pride, and malice, and couetouſneſſe, breach of charity, of Chriſtian, yea of naturall affection, hypocriſie, double-dealing, and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: (into which crimes many I feare, that thinke well of themſelues, and would be ſo thought of others, do yet run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and doe not heed it) nor on the other ſide will it ſerue our turnes to abſtaine in ſome good meaſure from violating the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the ſecond Table, (which fear or worldly ſhame, or other temporall reſpects may make vs carefull in) while wee make no conſcience of the Commandements of the firſt: perning our Religion with the Weathercockes of the time, diuiding our affections betweene God and <hi>Baal,</hi> allowing <hi>Dagon</hi> a roome as well as the Arke, gracing (as wee thinke) our ſpeeches with oathes and blaſphemies, making our ſelues Gentiles on Gods Sabbaths for feare of being Iewes. God hath ioyned theſe two tables together, the firſt he calls the great Commandement (and we make leaſt account of it) and of the ſecond he ſaith, that it is like vnto it, and no man muſt, (if he wil be a true Diſciple) ſeuer the things which God hath ioyned; they may be diſtinguiſhed in our bookes and learning, they muſt not bee diuided in our practice and liuing.</p>
            <p>Now, workes are then good, when, firſt, the ground of them is good, and that is the word of God, the touchſtone by which we muſt try, the compaſſe by which we muſt direct, the ſquare by which we muſt frame, and the rule whereby we muſt order all our actions, if wee will bring them within the compaſſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12430:6"/> religious good workes. Secondly, when the roote of them is good, and that is faith, without which, whatſoeuer hath the name of a good worke, hath yet as our Church ſpeakes (art. 13.) ſeeing not done as God hath willed, the nature of ſin in it; and all ſuch things though they appeare ſpecious and beautifull in the eies of men, yet are (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes) but <hi>splendida pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> they are not gold though they do gliſter. And thirdly, when the end of them is good, &amp; that is Gods glory: therefore ſayth our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi> And the Apoſtle, <hi>Whatſoeuer you doe, do all to the glory of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.31. And from good works thus vnderſtood and thus qualified, none are exempted, all haue their peeces of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, all haue their talents giuen them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. to ſome in one meaſure, and to other ſome in another, but to all to imploy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of their Maſter, and all to giue an account for their vſe of them; euery man hath his burthen, and hee muſt beare it himſelfe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5. Works of ſupererogation are works of ſuperarrogation, and he that wanting righteouſneſſe himſelfe hopeth to be ſaued by another mans, doth but mock himſelfe as Pope <hi>Symmachus</hi> did when he ſaid, and as the Canoniſts doe the Pope in ſaying ſo too (as it is <hi>diſt.</hi> 40. <hi>c. non nos.</hi>) that, <hi>In Papa ſi deſint bona acquiſita per meritum, &amp;c.</hi> If the Pope haue none or little goodneſſe of his owne (as it ſeemeth by this it may bee in that moſt holy Father himſelfe) he ſhall haue enough deriued vnto him from his Predeceſſor; if none in poſſeſſion, enough by ſucceſſion; if little by purchaſe, enough by inheritance: no, no, the Saints in heauen though they haue Crownes to weare, yet they haue none to ſpare: And, <hi>God ſhall reward euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his</hi> (not according to anothers) <hi>workes.</hi> Euery man is a tree, and ſhould be a good tree, whoſe root is faith, whoſe ſap is hope, whoſe branches, the ſeuerall branches of Gods Commandements, and <hi>of euery tree</hi> (without exception) <hi>that bringeth not forth good fruit,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10. <hi>it is cut downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> And, <hi>vpon euery ſoule of man that doth euill, ſhall bee tribulation and anguiſh,</hi> Rom. 2.9. O now, if I would looke about the world for a <hi>Dorcas,</hi> and in the troope of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples too, ſhould I not need with the Cynicke Philoſopher to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12430:6"/> light a candle, and yet ſhould not find? not many. <hi>The fruits of the spirit are loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Gal. 5.22. Theſe are fruits of faith, theſe are workes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. But where are theſe? And in ſtead of theſe, what are the too common fruits of faith? is your ſwearing and blaſphemy a fruit of faith? is your lying and periury a fruit of faith? and what ſay you to your riot and drunkenneſſe, to your chambering and wantonneſſe, to couetouſneſſe and oppreſſion, to vſury and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, to ſtrife and contention, to enuie and malice in one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, and the like to theſe? If theſe were the ſignes of Chriſtian profeſſion, if theſe were the badges of Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, if theſe were the works that God did looke for, God might come when he would, hee ſhould finde theſe things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, &amp; find vs full of them. O iudge with your ſelues (B.) is this the way to make your calling and election ſure? as <hi>S. Peter</hi> willeth you: or is it not the way rather to ſeale vnto your ſoules the aſſurance of your condemnation in the day of iudgment? No, no, if you will, as all good Chriſtians ought to doe, ſtriue to attaine to a certainty of your future bleſſedneſſe, theſe things ought not to be ſo among you; the workes of darkneſſe are not the way to heauen, the workes of righteouſneſſe are, though no meritorious cauſe of our comming thither. <hi>You muſt giue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all diligence, (for all will be little enough) <hi>to adde to your faith vertue,</hi> (for faith without workes is dead) <hi>to vertue knowledge,</hi> (or elſe you may doe that which is good, but you ſhall not doe it well) <hi>to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge temperance,</hi> (otherwiſe your knowledge will puffe you vp rather then edifie you) <hi>to temperance patience,</hi> (for as you muſt doe, ſo you ſhall ſuffer for your wel-doing) <hi>to patience god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> (for you may elſe giue your bodies to bee burnt in the fire, and it ſhall profit you nothing) <hi>to godlineſſe brotherly kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> (for how can he that loueth not his brother ſay truely that hee loueth God?) and <hi>to brotherly kindneſſe charity, or loue:</hi> (not onely brotherly kindneſſe to them that are of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith, but charity alſo towards all men, friends and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as Chriſt ſtretcht out his armes on the Croſſe to both the malefactors;) the firſt named of theſe things is faith, the laſt is loue, in the middle are other good workes, the ſumme of all is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12430:7"/> that, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Faith working by loue,</hi> if this bee in you, <hi>if theſe things be in you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>and abound, they will make you that you ſhall neither be barren nor vnfruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> neither inwardly barren, nor outwardly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull. And thus much concerning good workes in generall, for which this Matron in my Text is here commended; ſhe is commended in the next place in particular for her almeſ-deeds, an excellent ſpecies and member of thoſe good workes, to which we are enioyned. We haue precept for it, and example for it, and reaſons for it, in the holy Scriptures: <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters,</hi> ſaith the Preacher, <hi>Eccles</hi> 11.1. Firſt hee ſaith, <hi>caſt,</hi> doe not crumme it, doe not doe it lazily as if lothly, but giue it with a cheerfull minde: Secondly, <hi>Caſt bread,</hi> what is neceſſary for the ſuſtenance of them that need; and bread, not a a bone, that is for dogges; not a baſtinado, thats for rogues; nor <hi>panem lapidoſum,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeakes, bread full of grauell, ſuch as the hungry ſoule muſt needs eate, but it goeth downe heauily, becauſe it is giuen grudgingly: Thirdly, <hi>panem tuum,</hi> thy bread, that which thou haſt gotten with a good and an honeſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for to rob a Church, and then build a Spittle, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud or oppreſſe by the pound, and then deale a dole by the peny, is but (according to the well knowne prouerbe) to ſteale away the gooſe, and ſticke downe a feather; <hi>And he,</hi> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach, that bringeth an offering of the goods of the poore, doth as one that killeth the ſonne before his fathers eyes,</hi> Ecclus 34.20. And laſtly, it is ſaid, <hi>vpon the waters.</hi> Firſt, there diſtributed where there is no more hope of recompence, then of regaining that which is throwne into the Sea. Againe, ſaith God in the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Eſay c.</hi> 58.7. <hi>Is not this the faſt,</hi> firſt, this <hi>is the faſt that I haue choſen, to deale thy bread to the hungry, when thou ſeeſt the naked to couer him, and that thou hide not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh:</hi> In which laſt words a reaſon is giuen why the rich ſhould not turne away their eyes from the poore in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and diſdaine, as too commonly they doe, euen becauſe, they all are of the ſame mold &amp; fleſh, and among themſelues one anothers members. And laſtly the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Therefore</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as ye abound in euery thing, in faith &amp; vtterance, &amp;c. ſee that yee abound in this grace alſo, viz.</hi> a liberall contribution to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12430:7"/> of the poore, by the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 18. of <hi>Lot,</hi> Gen. 19. of <hi>Iob,</hi> who proteſted for himſelfe, <hi>that hee did not eate his morſels alone, but the fatherleſſe together with him,</hi> Iob 31.17. and by the example of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luk. 19.8. Nor are examples ſo many, but the benefit is as great. <hi>After many dayes thou ſhalt finde it.</hi> Eccles 11.1. And, <hi>The mercifull man doth good to his owne ſoul,</hi> Pro. 11.17. And, <hi>He that giueth to the poor, lendeth to the Lord, and what he hath giuen he will pay him again,</hi> Pro. 19.17. And, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) that conſidereth the poore and needy, the Lord ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble,</hi> Pſal. 41.1 And laſtly, <hi>Charge them that are rich</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,) that they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate, laying vp in ſtore for themſelues a good foundation againſt the time to come, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.18. I ſpeak not this by way of taxe, or as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning you, I know how the poore in this place are in very good meaſure prouided for: but I ſpeake you ſee to a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Country, as well as to you of the towne, and all are not alike minded neither among them or you. I pray God there be not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g both ſorts of you (though I know none here) ſome ſuch as in the world there are too many, who are <hi>humani in bellu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, &amp; in homines belluini,</hi> prodigall in their expenſes on hawks or horſes, or hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or worſe, &amp; yet cloſe fiſted the whil, &amp; ſquint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed when they ſhould look on and ſuccour their poore needy brethren: for them that are as in this caſe they ſhould be, what I haue ſpoken tends to their commendation and incouragement, and to the exhortation and ſtirring vp of others who are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like well minded, not alike as others, not alike as <hi>Dorcas</hi> in my text, of whom out of the words themſelues it may be truely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that euen while ſhe liued, <hi>ſhee was full of almes which ſhee did.</hi> She knew that in heauen ſhee ſhould meet with none that did none her helpe, and therefore ſhee would helpe them that needed before ſhe was going thither. I haue no reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne mens leauing to the poore by way of legacy in their laſt wills, yet ye know there is an old ſaying, that <hi>bis dat qui citò,</hi> that man doth giue double, that giueth ſeaſonably; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Heathen man could ſay, <hi>tantum gratiae demitur, quantum mora adijcitur:</hi> a good turne that is deferred and put off, doth loſe a great deale of that grace and thankes which otherwiſe it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12430:8"/> would haue, and a ſuſpition is left in the minds of men, that we giue therefore then, becauſe we cannot keepe it: <hi>non bona ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pauſat, quam benefacta Deus,</hi> God more reſpects the wel-doing of a thing, then the deed done: and indeed (Beloued) if no thing elſe did, the hardneſſe of theſe times, hard times for the poore certainly, doe euen force vs to open our hands as God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled vs, for their reliefe and ſuccour; O let vs not perſecute them whom God hath ſmitten, nor vexe them whom hee hath wounded; let not their affliction bee forgotten in the midſt of our feaſting. Plead not that the times are hard for others alſo, as well as for the poore: who will beleeue it that ſhall but thinke on this, that ſcarce was there euer more ſpent in pride and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, in ryot and gluttony, in quaſſing and carouſing, in ſports and gaming? and what a great deale of good might bee done to the poore, if they had what may well bee ſpared out of the coſtlineſſe of our apparell, out of the ſuperfluity of our diet, nay out of that that is beſtowed vpon the Deuill; for who elſe but he gaineth by what is caſt away in ryot and drunkenneſſe, in luſts and filthines, in games &amp; ſportfulneſſe, in needleſſe quarrels and contentions? doe not miſ-apply my words, I ſpeake in generall termes, and to forreiners from abroad, as well as to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this place; all whom I would haue to examine their owne ſoules; who take exception at what I ſpeake, doe but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray their owne guiltineſſe, and thinke a great deale worſe of themſelues then of me they can. O conſider (and ſo I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point) that it is <hi>panis eſurientium quem tu diuoras, &amp;c.</hi> the bread of the hungry which is deuoured in gluttony, the drinke of the thirſty that is ſwilled in intemperately; the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the naked that men ſtrut in ſo flauntingly (who ſome of them as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>parietes veſtiunt auro, &amp; pauperes nudant veſtimento,</hi> doe array their walls with cloth of Arras, of ſilke, of ſiluer, of gold, and leaue bare, if not make bare alſo the backes and armes of the needy) and the money of the poore peaceable ones which is caſt away in malitious ſures and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies. Let euery thing be placed in his due place, cauſe not the leane checkes to become lanker yet, make not the needy eyes to wait long, and bee euen ready to fall out of their ſockets with waiting; defraud not the poore of their due almes? though it be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12430:8"/> giuen vnto them, it is but lent vnto God, and he will repay it, and in due proportion too, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. <hi>He that ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reape ſparingly, and he that ſoweth bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhall reape bountifully:</hi> as of this godly matron in my Text it is ſaid, that ſhe ſowed bountifully, <hi>for ſhe was full of good works and almes which ſhe did.</hi> Concerning which words, it is noted, that <hi>fulneſſe</hi> here doth commend her good workes and almes, for three good qualities; ſincerity, generality, conſtancy; ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in reſpect of the root and fountaine, generality in reſpect of the ſtreames and branches, and conſtancy in reſpect of the growth and current, her goodneſſe proceeded from her heart, did ſpread it ſelfe farre and wide, and did continue and laſt vnto her end.</p>
            <p>And now (Beloued) that in the midſt of our fulneſſe in other kinds, fulnes of pride, fulnes of idlenes, fulneſſe of knowledge, and fulneſſe of good words, wee would be full of good workes alſo as ſhe was: If we do good, is it not grudgingly, or for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and temporal reſpects? where is our fulneſſe of ſincerity then? Is it not mincingly, and with that great perſonages limitation, in the booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> God be mercifull vnto vs in theſe and theſe caſes? where is our fulneſſe of generality then? Or is it not weariſomely and with great fainting? where is our fulneſſe of conſtancy and perſeuerance? It is this being full of goodneſſe that bringeth glory vnto God, <hi>for herein is my Father glorified,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>that you beare much fruit,</hi> Ioh. 15.8. It bringeth aſſurance to our conſciences of our happy eſtate here, <hi>for he that abideth in me and I in him,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>the ſame bringeth forth much fruit,</hi> Ioh. 15.5. and of the reward of bleſſedneſſe laid vp for vs in heauen, therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Let vs not be weary in well doing, for in due time wee ſhall reape if wee faint not:</hi> if not now while we liue, (and indeed their caſe is the worſt of all of whom it may be ſaid, <hi>they haue their reward</hi>) yet aſſuredly when death commeth, as it did to this good woman in my text, and is the ſecond generall thing I muſt ſpeake of concerning her, the death of <hi>Dorcas,</hi> with the immediate fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner thereof her ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it came to paſſe in thoſe daies, that ſhe was ſicke, and dyed.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Now the word that is here read <hi>it came to paſſe,</hi> is ſometimes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12430:9"/> read, it fortuned or happened, both well in diuers reſpects, the one in reſpect of God, vnto whoſe prouidence all things being ſubiect, and gouerned by it, it is ſaid in regard thereof, that things come to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe; and yet to chance or happen in reſpect of vs vnto whom God thinkes not fit to reueale and open thoſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euents, which hee mindeth to kepe in his owne hands. Whence the point collected is that which you all know, that there is nothing can befall man in this world, be it cloudy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or cleere, ſunſhine, or full of ſtormes, but it is all ſubiect and ſubordinate to the wiſdome and prouidence of Almighty God. There be other names vſed among men, as fate and deſtiny, and the like; but heare what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, (<hi>de ciuit. Dei, l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1) <hi>Qua ſi propterea quis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fato tribuit, &amp;c.</hi> If any man attribute the things that come to paſſe vnto fate or deſtiny, and ſay that by it he meanes the will and prouidence of God, <hi>Sententiam teneat, linguam corrigat,</hi> let him keepe his opinion, but let him alter his phraſe of ſpeech, becauſe many when they heare theſe words, fate, deſtiny, and the like, are moued to beleue the ſome thing inferiour vnto Gods prouidence is meant, as the cauſe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer of the things that happen: and the leſſon hence ariſing is in a word this, that in all the changes and chances of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, we lay vp our reſt vpon Gods prouidence, and next after our honeſt and lawfull endeauors refer the ſucceſſe of all to him: in time of health and proſperity, not lifted vp with pride and preſumption; nor murmuring and repining when wee ſee the hand of God vpon vs, (though we ſee the hand of men, or the Deuill there alſo) in caſe of croſſe and aduerſity; but alwaies reſoluing as old <hi>Ely</hi> did, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good. It came to paſſe that ſhee was ſicke,</hi> yea ſickneſſe is the ſuburbs through which ordinarily wee doe enter into the gates of death: and for this purpoſe hath God placed in mans body deaths armory, his fort of munition, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hang a thouſand ſhields, wherewith the Lieutenant and his Captaine, the meſſenger and his maſter, <hi>morbus</hi> and <hi>mors,</hi> ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death, doe but come and then ouercome man. Mans head and heart, and ſtomacke, and lyuer, and lights, and lungs, and other parts of his body, what are they, but ſo many ſeuerall cells wherin ſickneſſe and death haue ſeuerall ſwords to wound
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12430:9"/> and kill man with when God will haue it ſo. Nay, man ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> is alwaies ſicke of one diſeaſe or other, generally of three aboue other, the one in his beginning and entrance into the world, and that is full of infirmity and vncleanneſſe: the ſecond in his progreſſe through the world, and that is full of iniquitie and peruerſneſſe: the third in his going out of the world, not without paine and perill: and <hi>naſci in corpore mortali aegrotare eſt,</hi> to be born into the world, is to be thruſt out into a Spittlehouſe. And if we conſider almoſt the whole courſe of a mans life, how it is ſpent, we ſhall finde it compoſed of nothing elſe, but infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities &amp; remedies, maladies and medicines, ſickneſſes and their phyſick, and the phyſicke and remedies many times more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome then the diſeaſes themſelues; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man is hungry he is not well till he eat, &amp; labor killeth without reſt after it; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the one to cure the paine of the other, and yet ofttimes eating makes as ſicke as hunger did, the reſt of the body yeelds no reſt to the mind, and the time of quiet proues the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet time of all. <hi>It came to paſſe that ſhe was ſicke;</hi> What, this godly and charitable matron? yea, and no maruaile at it, the Lord chaſteneth whom he loueth, and afflicteth with ſome kind of croſſe or other euery ſonne whom he doth receiue, and <hi>qui excipitur è numero flagellatorum, excipitur è numero filiorum, They that are altogether without correction, are baſtards and not ſonnes,</hi> Heb. 12.8. But it proues in Gods children, though harſh to fleſh and blood, as the clay by our Sauiour Chriſts po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, did to the blinde man, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. an excellent meanes to open thoſe eyes which were ſhut by ſinne, and make a man ſee both Gods power, and his owne weakneſſe, which in time of eaſe and freedome he did not ſo well diſcerne: for the fruit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome groweth on the tree of trouble, and the ſchoolehouſe of affliction is the ſchoolehouſe of inſtruction. But if iudgement be executed on the houſe of God, where ſhall the wicked and ſinners appeare? the one are corrected in the world, that they may not be condemned with the world; and the other let alone oft-times to ſpend their daies as oxen in fat paſtures, of purpoſe to be reſerued for a more grieuous ſlaughter. O then, if you will that death ſhall not be terrible when it comes (though the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher calls it of all terrible things the worſt) learne firſt to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12430:10"/> bid the forerunners of death welcome; learne to entertaine, as ye ought ſickneſſes patiently, the ſickneſſes of the body; and croſſes patiently, the croſſes of the minde; and loſſes patiently, loſſe of goods, loſſe of friends, loſſe of liberty; if God doe ſo order it, theſe are <hi>anteambulones,</hi> the <hi>prodromi,</hi> the footpoſts, the meſſengers, the harbingers of death; bid (I ſay) theſe welcome and death ſhall come well vnto you when it comes, as come it will, perhaps as neere to the heeles of ſickneſſe, as the words in my text doe come cloſe together, <hi>ſhe was ſick, and dyed.</hi> Or if not, as not alwaies, yet are there two wormes, the two daughters of Time, Day and Night, which continually bite and gnaw at the root of the tree; our very life and hart-blood, while we, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall of that whereof to bee couetous is the onely couetouſneſſe that is honeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> our time, doe ſo long feed on the honey-combes that hang ouer out heads, deſiring to ſatiate our ſelues with the pleaſures of this life, till this tree of our life bee bitten through by thoſe two worms, and we fall into that pit whence there is no redemption. <hi>She was ſicke and dyed.</hi> Yea, this is the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ordinary effect of ſickneſſe, that ſooner or later it will end in death; <hi>ſhe was ſicke and dyed: and man is ſicke, and dyeth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, c.</hi> 14.10. but what meanes <hi>Iob</hi> ſo immediately to the former words <hi>man is ſicke,</hi> to adioyne thoſe other, <hi>and man dyeth,</hi> why doth he ſo? Is it to aggrauate the miſeries to which poore man in this world is ſubiect? by the whole ſcope of the text it ſhould ſeeme it is, and yet how can it be ſo? <hi>for man is ſicke and dyeth,</hi> is no more then man hath gone a long and a weariſome pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and hath finiſhed his courſe, or man hath laboured and wearied himſelfe al the day long, and is ſet him downe to reſt; or man hath ouer-watcht himſelfe and is falne aſleepe: this is <hi>man is ſicke, and dyeth:</hi> death indeed, the remembrance of death is bitter to the man that is at reſt in his poſſeſſions, that hath nothing to vexe him, but hath proſperity in all things, whoſe breſts are yet full of milke, and his bones of marrow, who may waſh his plants with butter, and whoſe rocks powre him out riuers of oyle; O how would the newes of death make him ſtartle, and his knees ſmite each other with trembling, as it fared with <hi>Foelix</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned of the iudgment to come. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25. But when a man ſhal long for death, as a ſeruant doth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12430:10"/> for the ſhadow, an hireling for the end of his worke, and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in trauell for her deliuery: when he would ſeeke for death if hee knew where, as a man would ſeeke for treaſures, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce if he could finde the graue: whoſe cheekes are gummy with weeping, and the picture of death ſits in his eyes, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eates morſell with pleaſure, but is ſtill dying in the bitternes of his ſoule: to ſuch a man how acceptable would the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death be, and to dye after ſickneſſe no degree of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Indeed if wee conſider death as adioyned to that world of miſeries which in this world of miſery we are ſubiect to, then is death a more excellent medicine then all the Art of man can preſcribe, to cure all diſeaſes: but if in the cauſe of it which was ſinne, and in the nature of it, euen the diſſolution of nature; then doth fleſh bid away to death, though it be the ordinance of the Lord ouer all fleſh; yea all. The words of <hi>Iob</hi> doe ſhew the Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of all mankind, <hi>I haue ſaid to corruption, thou art my father, and to the wormes, thou art my mother, and my ſiſter,</hi> Iob 17.14. And if King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid perſonally of himſelfe, prophetical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his Lord and ours, <hi>I am a worme and no man,</hi> what man is there that is not a worme alſo? This we know well enough all of vs, euen ſo well that the Deuill himſelfe cannot make vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the contrary, he dares not ſay to vs as he did to our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>ye ſhall not dye,</hi> they had ſeene none dye before them, wee haue had millions, yet ſee how eaſily he makes fooles of vs, hee chokes vs with the ſame bait as he did them, but with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, he gaue them the bait whole and they ſwallowed it, he giues it vs by peeces, as that we ſhall not dye yet, not this day, or this weeke, or this moneth, or perhaps not this yeare; and ſo quickly perſwades vs ſo to liue, as if we were immortall, neuer dreaming either of deaths certainty, or hells miſery, or heauens felicity.</p>
            <p>The due conſideration of which things, euen of death alone, would ſerue to humble vs, as it did thoſe Ancients, who made their often caſting aſhes on their heads, a monument and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of their mortality: it would ſerue to worke repentance in vs as it did in the <hi>Niniuites;</hi> and that excellent reſolution which it did in <hi>Iob,</hi> when hee ſaid, <hi>Naked came I out of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord giueth and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12430:11"/> the Lord taketh away;</hi> (liuing as well as life, and life as well as liuing) <hi>bleſſed be the name of the Lord</hi> for all, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.21. It would bee auailable againſt the luſt of the eies, couetouſneſſe, for hee might eaſily be perſwaded not to loue the world, that would duely conſider how ſoone hee might leaue the world, and the things of it: againſt pride of life it would bee auailable, for what ſhould make him lift vp his heart aboue his brethren, whoſe head hee may happe to trample vnder his feet that now kneeles before him? O if a man would but thinke on it, how vile Chriſt became for him, &amp; what himſelf is in himſelf, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his birth, wickedneſſe in his life, the ſubiect of rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his end: in his comming into the world miſerable, in his liuing in the world ſinfull, in his going out of the world the heire of corruption, if not the child of perdition too, this would make to ſtoope the necke of pride as white as Iuory which muſt ſhortly be as the clay in the ſtreets. And laſtly, againſt the luſts of the fleſh which though neuer ſo much doted on, and euen made an Idoll of, muſt firſt breed a multitude of wormes, then be deuoured of them; nay, there are three things that wait to ſhare vs and what we haue betweene them, the wormes to haue our fleſh, the world to haue our wealth, and the Deuill to haue our ſoules; and euery of theſe ſo well contented with his owne part, that he will not leaue it for both the other: the world will not care for our ſoules, or for our bodies, ſo it may haue our goods; the wormes will not care for our goods or for our ſoules, ſo they may haue our bodies; and the Deuill will not care for our bodies or for our goods, ſo he may haue our ſoules: but let vs therefore care more then we doe, if not for our bodies, (let death make his beſt of them that he can) yet for our ſubſtance and for our ſoules, to put both our houſes in order before wee dye; our outward and our inward houſe, the one for ſetling of peace both our owne and theirs whom wee leaue behinde vs, and the other for our ſoules eternall happineſſe; and both theſe, becauſe it may be ſaid to any of vs <hi>thou ſhalt dye and not liue,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can be ſaid <hi>put thine houſe in order,</hi> that ſo the houſes eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of our hearts may be in order alwaies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>And thus we haue followed <hi>Dorcas</hi> as farre as my text did lead vs; Is there now euer another <hi>Dorcas</hi> for me to ſpeake of?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12430:11"/> ſure this towne had, and <hi>habuiſſe decus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of the graces and godly end of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi>Mary Bab.</hi>
               </note> it is a credit to them that they had, for ſhee was a credit to them while they had her, in a good degree ſuch another <hi>Dorcas:</hi> Concerning whom though I ſhould be ſilent, and ſhall be ſparing, yet this Church which ſhe duely frequented, thoſe poore whom ſhe continually relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, this towne which ſhe alwayes loued, nay not <hi>Ioppa</hi> onely, and this her dwelling place, but all that knew her by acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and many other that did not know her but by the eare, will yet ſay, (and it will be ſaid hereafter perhaps with more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling then now) that this place hath loſt a <hi>Dorcas,</hi> who was, as the name I told you ſignified in the root of it, cleare-ſighted, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke herſelfe how ſhe ſhould, and to prouide in ſome meaſure that ſhe might ſo lead her life here, that ſhee might afterwards liue eternally with God, as her good life, and right Chriſtian end doe aſſure vs that ſhe now doth. Why, is ſhee dead then? what elſe meanes our meeting here at this time? what this great concourſe of people? in all whoſe faces a man may eaſily read the loue and griefe, that brought you hither: and ſhall I not think you thought her worthy of loue? I am ſure you had reaſon ſo to doe; you the poore of this place, to whom I cannot ſay, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> to the Daughters of <hi>Iſrael, weepe for</hi> Saul <hi>that clothed you in Scarlet,</hi> but weepe for <hi>Dorcas</hi> who was alwaies ready, and to her end, and at her end, to ſuccour and releeue in great meaſure your wants and neceſſities; wherein if other women did well, yet ſhee ſurmounted them. Yet doe not weepe for her, weepe for your ſelues, and for your ſinnes; ſerue God in holineſſe and godlineſſe of liuing; expreſſe ſo your thankes to God for bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntinuing her ſo long among you, (till ſhee was aged fourſcore yeares and fiue) for your good, and then doubt not but if ye ſerue God as ye ought, hee will prouide for you as you need: or elſe feare that God will take away more <hi>Dorcaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> from you (if at leaſt there bee more) and it fare worſe with you yet then now it doth. But our <hi>Dorcas</hi> did not dye till ſhe was ſicke firſt, and in her ſickneſſe, O how did God ſhew that whom hee loueth, hee loueth to the end, and toward the end expreſſeth it more abundantly, as he did to her, who, as if ſhee knew that this ſickneſſe ſhould be her laſt, and becauſe ſhe knew that the leaſt thought of worldly things is of force to withdraw
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12430:12"/> the mind from neceſſary meditations, left preſently the care of theſe things to others, whom by her Will many yeares before made, ſhe had truſted with theſe things; &amp; ſpent euen al the reſt of her time (as I am and you may be informed by thoſe to whoſe report you can make no ſcruple to giue credit) in a right Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian preparation for her laſt end, by an often confeſſion of her truſt in God, ſorrowfull acknowledgement of her owne wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, admirable patience in the middeſt of her paines, earneſt deſires to be with her Sauiour, yet with Chriſtian ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of her will to Gods, to the great comfort of them that came to comfort her, till euen at her laſt moment, as if ſhee ſaw heauen open, and her Sauiour ready to receiue her into his armes, ſhee deſired to be heaued vp into the armes of her Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who did not ſtay long from her, nor would let her ſtay long from him, but receiued her ſoule into his heauenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, leauing her body to be by vs brought vnto it long home, there to ſleepe in its bed of reſt, till at the laſt day it riſe againe, and be made partaker of that endleſſe happineſſe which her ſoule in the meane while doth alone enioy; and whereto God in his due time bring vs all, for his great mercies ſake, and the merits of his Sonne and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. To whom, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>Her Epitaph.</head>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>D</hi>Eare is the death, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> in God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>F all his Saints: of her among the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>Ich in good workes, and almes, and day and night,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>Arefull to ſerue God, loued of the beſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>Ged in yeares, in goodneſſe, mercy, loue:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>Hee ſickned, died: and now doth liue aboue.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12430:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
